Aline and Eero Saarinen
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Aline Saarinen Professional Papers, 1906-1969, Series 2:; (Boxes 4-14, 15, OV 16; 9.8 linear) feet)
  - Research Material on Stanford White, 1880s-1969, 2.3:
    - Original Material, 1880s-1936, 1960, 2.3.4:
      - McKim, Mead and White Documents (Box 10)
        - Correspondence, 1905-1906 (Box 10, Folder 28)
        - Correspondence, 1923 (Box 10, Folder 29)
        - Correspondence, 1933, 1935 (Box 10, Folder 30)
        - The Metropolitan Club, undated (Box 10, Folder 31)
        - Madison Square Presbyterian Church, 1903 (Box 10, Folder 32)
        - The Colony Club, undated (Box 10, Folder 33)
        - Actor's Fund Fair, undated (Box 10, Folder 34)
        - Plan for Unidentified Building (blueprint), undated (Box 10, Folder 35)
        - Fairmont Park, 1895 (Box 10, Folder 36)
        - Vanderbilt Portal, St. Bartholomew's Church, 1902, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 37)
        - Columbian Celebration Awards, undated (Box 10, Folder 38)
        - Arch at Washington Square, 1889 (Box 10, Folder 39)
        - Tiffany Building, 1903 (Box 10, Folder 40)
        - Whitelaw Reid Residence - Estimate, Proposal, and Report on Progress, 1890-1891 (Box 10, Folder 41)
        - Whitelaw Reid Residence - Correspondence, 1891, (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 42-43)
        - Whitelaw Reid Residence - Correspondence, 1892 (Box 10, Folder 44)
        - Whitelaw Reid Residence - Correspondence, 1893 (Box 10, Folder 45)
        - Whitelaw Reid Residence - Correspondence, 1894 (Box 10, Folder 46)
        - Whitelaw Reid Residence - Correspondence, 1895 (Box 10, Folder 47)
        - Whitelaw Reid Residence - Correspondence, 1896-1899 (Box 10, Folder 48)
        - Whitelaw Reid Residence - Correspondence, undated (Box 10, Folder 49)
        - Whitelaw Reid Residence - Clipping, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 50)
        - Grant Monument, undated (Box 10, Folder 51)
        - University of Virginia, 1923, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 52)
        - Arlington Memorial Bridge, undated (Box 10, Folder 53)
        - Record Book, "Antiques at 120 W 30", 1905 (Box 10, Folder 54)
      - Microfilmed Correspondence of Richard Grant White (circa 25 letters) and Stanford White (1 letter) from Huntington Library, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 55)
    - Printed Material, 1890s-1968, 2.3.5:
      Printed material collected by Aline Saarinen in the course of her research consists primarily of clippings and publications with articles on White, his buildings, and certain people associated with him. Also found is miscellaneous printed material on the Garden City Hotel, Newport, RI, and architecture.
      - Clippings (Box 10)
        - Stanford White, 1896-1898 (Box 10, Folder 56)
        - Stanford White, 1919, 1931-1936, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 57)
        - Stanford White, 1960, 1962 (Box 10, Folder 58)
        - Stanford White, undated (Box 10, Folder 59)
        - Stanford White, Auctions, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 60)
        - Players' Club,1890s? (Box 10, Folder 61)
        - Madison Square Presbyterian Church, 1906 (Box 10, Folder 62)
        - Madison Square Garden, 1890s, (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 63-64)
        - Madison Square Garden, Horse Show, 1890s (Box 10, Folder 65)
        - New York, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 66)
        - Garden of J. L. Breese, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 67)
        - Article on Architecture by Lawrence Grant White, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 68)
        - Building and Designs of Stanford White, Various, 1932-1968 (Box 10, Folder 69)
        - Evelyn Nesbit, 1905, 1954 (Box 10, Folder 70)
        - Amelie Rives Chanler, 1895-1897 (Box 10, Folder 71)
      - Other Printed Material on Stanford White and His Buildings, 1955-1967, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 10, Folder 72)
      - Garden City Hotel (Long Island, NY), circa 1894 (Box 10, Folder 73)
      - Newport, RI and "The Breakers", 1946-1963, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 10, Folder 74)
      - Miscellaneous Printed Material on Architecture, 1928-1960, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 10, Folder 75)
      - Miscellaneous Printed Material, undated (Box 10, Folder 76)
    - Photographs, 1880s-circa 1960, 2.3.6:
      Photographs include ones of Stanford White and his family, his clients, Anne, Louise, and Robert Cheney, and his one-time mistress, Evelyn Nesbit; and ones of buildings and residences designed by White or McKim, Mead and White, many of which were photographed by Wayne Andrews. Also found are photographs of interiors and slides and negatives of certain photographs of buildings and residences.
      - Stanford White and His Family, 1880s-1890s (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - The Cheney Family, 1880s? (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Evelyn Nesbit, 1890s-1902 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - Buildings and Residences Designed by Stanford White, 1960, undated, (7 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 11, Folder 4-10)
      - Residences in Newport, RI Designed by Stanford White and McKim, Mead and White, 1960, undated, (2 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 11, Folder 11-12)
      - Residences Designed by Stanford White and McKim, Mead and White, 1960, undated, (3 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 11, Folder 13-15)
      - Views of Interiors, Various, undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - Views of Interiors, Unidentified, undated (Box 11, Folder 17)
      - Slides, Buildings Designed by Stanford White and McKim, Mead and White, circa 1960, (Not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 18)
      - Negatives, Buildings Designed by Stanford White and McKim, Mead and White, circa 1960, (Not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Architectural Drawings, undated, 2.3.7:
      Included are reproductions and negatives of architectural drawings for various buildings and residences, which date from 1884 to 1903, designed by White or McKim, Mead and White.
      - Reproductions of Architectural Drawings, undated, (See also OV 16) (Box 11, Folder 20)
      - Negatives, Architectural Drawings, undated, (Not scanned) (Box 11, Folder 21)
      - Oversize, Reproductions of Architectural Drawings, undated, (See Box 11, F20) (Box OV 16)
  - NBC Correspondent Files, 1961-1971, 2.4:; (Not scanned)
    Subseries consists of files kept by Aline Saarinen while working as a television correspondent for NBC on such shows as "Today", "Sunday", and "The Hunter-Brinkley Report", reporting on mainly art-related topics. Files include correspondence, printed material, notes, scripts, clippings, motion picture films and video transfers, and photographs. Also included are printed material on Eero Saarinen and photographs of his work.
    Files are arranged alphabetically according to subject or format.
    - The 101 Ranch (Oklahoma), 1965 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Amon Carter Museum, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Astronauts, 1965, (4 folders; see also Box 15) (Box 11, Folder 24-27)
    - Biltmore House and Gardens, circa 1965 (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - "Blacks and Art", undated (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - Clippings, 1964-1971, (3 folders) (Box 11, Folder 30-32)
    - Clippings, Articles by Aline Saarinen, 1964, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - Computer Art, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence, 1963-1971 (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 1967, undated (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - Engagement Calendar, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 37)
    - Federal Building Design, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 38)
    - Films (Box 12)
      - "Art Special" Sunday Show: Eyes Opening (video transfer), 1964 May 24, (2 folders) (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
      - The Metropolitan Museum with John Lindsay (video tranfer), 1970, (2 folders) (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
      - "Mobile Homes" (16 mm film), undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - "Out-Take" (16 mm film), undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Gemini 9 Material, circa 1966 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Held, John, 1964 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - "Hemisfair '68", 1968 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Marine Amputee Story, 1967, (2 folders) (Box 12, Folder 10-11)
    - Metropolitan Museum, 1970, (2 folders) (Box 12, Folder 12-13)
    - Museum of Modern Art, 1964 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Notebooks (Box 12)
      - Grand Canyon, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - "Hawthorne and Alcott", 1960s (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - "Script - Film Schedule - Dept. List", undated (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Notes and Drafts, 1960s (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - "Osaka" (Japanese World Exposition), 1968 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Pavilion Hotel (Montpelier, VT), 1965-1966 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Peterson, Susan (Reporter for Bissell Inc.), 1960s (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Photographs of Buildings and Memorial Designed by Eero Saarinen, 1960s (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Photographs of Saarinen Home in Helsinki, Finland, undated (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Photographs of Aline Saarinen on Assignment and from Shows, 1960s, (4 folders) (Box 13, Folder 1-4)
    - Photographs, Portraits of Aline Saarinen, circa 1965 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Photograph of Aline Saarinen, Contemporary Press Course, Vassar College, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Press Pass, Democratic National Convention, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Press Releases and Other Printed Material, 1963-1970 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Printed Material, Miscellaneous, 1970, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Protest, Internal Revenue Service, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Quotes, 1962-1963 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Regan, Nancy, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Religious Architecture, 1963, undated (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - "Remote Possibilities" (Gallery of Art Interpretation designed by Katherine Kuh, The Art Institute of Chicago), undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Resume and Awards, 1964-1969 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Rockefeller, Nelson, 1965-1969, (2 folders) (Box 13, Folder 16-17)
    - Rockefeller, Nelson - Photograph of Art Work from Collection, undated (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Saarinen, Eero, 1961-1971 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Scripts (Box 13)
      - Frank McGee Reports, 1966, undated (Box 13, Folder 20)
      - "From Here to the Seventies", 1969 (Box 13, Folder 21)
      - The Huntley-Brinkley Report, 1966-1968, undated, (2 folders) (Box 13, Folder 22-23)
      - "Israel: From this Hill", 1965 (Box 13, Folder 24)
      - Sixth Hour, 1967, undated (Box 13, Folder 25)
      - The Southern Baptist Hour, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 26)
      - Sunday Show, 1964-1965 (Box 13, Folder 27)
      - Today Show, 1963-1969, (5 folders) (Box 13, Folder 28-32)
      - "Year Ender Script", 1964 (Box 13, Folder 33)
      - Miscellaneous, 1960s, (4 folders) (Box 13, Folder 34-37)
    - The Southern Baptist Hour, "Art and the Bible", 1969 (Box 13, Folder 38)
    - Storyboard (?), undated (Box 13, Folder 39)
    - "Sunday Artists", 1964, (2 folders) (Box 13, Folder 40-41)
    - "Sunday Artists" (Box 13)
      - Arp, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 42)
      - Calder, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 43)
      - Davis, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 44)
      - Giacometti, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 45)
      - Miro, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 46)
      - Moore, 1964 (Box 13, Folder 47)
    - Vietnam, 1965, (3 folders) (Box 13, Folder 48-50)
    - Writings on Art, 1960s (Box 13, Folder 51)
    - Writing on Saigon, circa 1965 (Box 13, Folder 52)
    - Yugoslavia, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 53)
    - Oversize, Astronauts, 1965 (Box 15 (sol))
  - Miscellaneous Research Files, circa 1960-1964, undated, 2.5:
    Subseries consists of files stemming from Aline Saarinen's research on various artists and relating to miscellaneous or unidentified projects. Files mostly include notes and correspondence. Of particular note is a letter from Georgia O'Keeffe referring to Saarinen's idea of "a color film story" about the artist.
    Files are arranged alphabetically according to subject.
    - Held Jr., John, undated (Box 14 (hol), Folder 1)
    - Lawrence, Jacob, circa 1960 (Box 14 (hol), Folder 2)
    - McCarter, Henry, undated (Box 14 (hol), Folder 3)
    - O'Keeffe, Georgia, 1964 (Box 14 (hol), Folder 4)
    - Outline, Unidentified Project, undated (Box 14 (hol), Folder 5)
  - Committee Files, 1961-1968, 2.6:
    Subseries consists of files relating to Saarinen's participation on various committees, boards, and commissions, including the Design Advisory Committee for the Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) which recommended I. M. Pei's design for a standard air traffic control tower. Files include reports, minutes, printed material, correspondence, and photographs. Also found is correspondence and a partial manuscript for a proposed article on Najeeb Halaby of the FAA for Harper's Magazine.
    Files are arranged in chronological order.
    - Design Advisory Committee, Federal Aviation Adminstration, 1961-1962, (3 folders) (Box 14 (hol), Folder 6-8)
    - Fine Arts Commission, 1964-1967, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 14 (hol), Folder 9)
    - Yale University, 1962-1966 (Box 14 (hol), Folder 10)
    - Yale-New Haven Educational Corporation, Board of Directors, 1967-1968, (2 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 14 (hol), Folder 11-12)